<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sinfulnesse of sinne ; and, The fulnesse of Christ delivered in two sermons / by William Bridge.</title>
            <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4466A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09722078</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09722078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1350:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sinfulnesse of sinne ; and, The fulnesse of Christ delivered in two sermons / by William Bridge.</title>
                  <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
                  <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670. Fulnesse of Christ.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35, 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The fulnesse of Christ" has separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44040:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44040:1"/>
            <p>THE SINFULNESSE OF SINNE, AND THE FULNESSE OF CHRIST. Delivered in Two Sermons, By Mr. WILLIAM BRIDGE. Sometime Fellow of <hi>Emanuel</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and 'late Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44040:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44040:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou art deſired to take notice, That theſe two Sermons are not expoſed to publique view by the Author's own hand, but were taken as they fell from his lips in his ordinary Preaching: Nevertheleſs, the ſtyle, method, ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, conciſeneſs, and depth of them, give in ample teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to all that have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb facs="tcp:44040:3"/> with him, that they are his genuine off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring; And being ſuitable and uſefull to all perſons, in all conditions, thou mayeſt (through the bleſſing of God) reap much advantage by them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44040:3"/>
            <head>THE SINFULNESSE OF SINNE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 7. and part of the 13 Verſe.</bibl> But ſin, that it might appear ſin, working death in me by that which is good: that ſin by the Commandment might become ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſinful.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>MY purpoſe is now to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning the evil and ſinfulneſs of ſin, and therefore have made choice of theſe words. In this Chapter the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth give us ſome account of the way and manner of his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Before I was converted (ſayes he) <hi>I was alive without the Law,</hi> (ver. 9.) <hi>but when</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44040:4"/> 
               <hi>the Commandment came, ſin revived and I died;</hi> for without the Law ſin was dead, and <hi>I was alive without the Law once.</hi> I thought my ſelf a jolly man, I was very brisk and jolly; had good thoughts of my condition; <hi>I was alive without the Law once, but when the Commandment came,</hi> when the word of the Lord came in power unto my ſoul; for I had the Law, and the Commandment always with me: <hi>Concerning the Law,</hi> I was <hi>blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> Phil. 3. 6. the letter of the Law was not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from me: but when it pleaſed God to ſet on the Word of the Lord in power upon my ſoul; then, whereas I was alive before, now ſin revived: ſin that lay dead before, and was hid, now revived, and did appear to be ſin; for that in the 9 Verſe, and this in the 13, are the ſame: Verſ. 9. <hi>Sin revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and I died: but ſin, that it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſin, working death in me;</hi> in this 13 Verſe. But how did ſin revive, and appear? By the coming of the Law, by the coming of the Commandment, thereby it broke out the more, and ſo was diſcovered; as by the coming and ſhining of the Sun-beams upon the Dung-hill, the filth ſtinks the more; not that the Sun-beams are the cauſe, but the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereof. And ſin revived by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44040:4"/> of the Commandment, and appeared to be ſin, appeared more to me in its own ſhape, and ſtruck me dead with the appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof; whereas before, ſin was dead, and I alive, now ſin alive, and I dead.</p>
            <p>From whence then I take up this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> That there is a great deal of evil and ſinfulneſs in ſin, which doth not appear to a man, until he doth Convert, and turn unto God. Look when a man doth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and turn unto God, then ſin appears to be ſin indeed, and not before.</p>
            <p>For the clearing and proſecution whereof I ſhall labour to ſhew,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That there is a great deal of evil, and ſinfulneſs in ſin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That this evil, and ſinfulneſs of ſin, doth not appear to a man, until Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion-work paſs upon his ſoul.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Look when a man doth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and turn to the Lord in truth, then ſin appears in the ſinfulneſs thereof unto him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a great deal of evil and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſin.</p>
            <p>To make it out in the general, and then more particularly;</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the general, this may appear by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44040:5"/> names of ſin, for ſin hath taken up all the names of evil of all evils. The Scripture doth not Nickname ſin, and yet what evil is there incident unto man, but ſin is inveſted with the name thereof in Scripture?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it an evil thing for a man to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean and filthy? Sin is called filthineſs: <hi>I will waſh you from all your filthineſs,</hi> Ezek. 36. 25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it an evil thing for a man to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? Sin is called nakedneſs: <hi>That your nakedneſs may not appear,</hi> Rev. 3. 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is it an evil thing for a man to be blind? Sin is called blindneſs: <hi>The blind ſhall lead the blind,</hi> Mat. 15. 14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it an evil thing for a man to be fooliſh? Sin is called folly. <hi>That you may no more return unto folly,</hi> Pſal. 85. 8.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is it an evil thing for a man to be mad? The Prodigal returned unto himſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 17, and <hi>I was mad,</hi> ſayes <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 26. 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Is it an evil thing for a man to be dead? Sin is called death: <hi>Dead in treſpaſses and ſins.</hi> Epheſ. 2. 1.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is called an Abomination, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 7. and becauſe there is no word that can expreſs the evil and ſinfulneſs of ſin, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44040:5"/> in this place ſayes, <hi>That ſin might become exceeding ſinful.</hi> Why? Becauſe there is no word of evil that can reach the evil of ſin. Now look what that is that doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs and take up all the names of all evils that muſt needs be exceeding evil; So it is with ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Look what that is that doth ſeparate betwixt us and God, who is the chiefeſt and univerſal good; That muſt needs be the greateſt evil. Now ſayes the Prophet, <hi>Your iniquities have ſeparated between you and your God,</hi> Iſa. 59. 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Look what that is that doth unite us to Satan, and make us the Children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; That muſt needs be very evil: Says our Saviour, <hi>You are of your father the devil.</hi> Why? <hi>For his works you do,</hi> Joh. 8. 44. Sin makes us the children of the devil.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Look what that is that did put Chriſt to death, that was the cauſe of his death; That muſt needs be exceeding evil. So ſin did: <hi>He was made ſin for us,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 21. <hi>He bare our ſins upon the Croſs,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 24. <hi>and the Lord made the iniquity of us all to meet on him,</hi> Iſa. 53. 6.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Look what that is that doth bring a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral curſe upon the whole Creation; That muſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44040:6"/> needs be evil: So ſin hath done; <hi>curſed be the ground, and the earth for thy ſake,</hi> Gen. 3. 17.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Look what that is that doth ſoil and ſtain all our glory, and the Image of God in us; That muſt needs be great evil. Sin hath ſtayned the beauty of the Image of God that was ſtampt upon us, and by ſin, ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Row.</hi> 3. 23. we come ſhort of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, <hi>For all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Look what that is, that doth bring ſuch horror of Conſcience that a ſoul is not able to bear, and cannot be allayed but by the blood of Jeſus; That muſt needs be a very great evil: Sin, and the eating of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit hath bred this worm that never dies.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Look what that evil is, that is the few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el of Hell, that feeds Hell-fire to all Eternity; That muſt needs be great evil: Take ſin away and Hell-fire dies: Sin is that brimſtone that Hell-fire feeds upon to all Eternity.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Look what that Evil is, that is worſe than the worſt of afflictions; That muſt needs be very evil: The leaſt ſin is worſe than the greateſt affliction: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take an affliction, and though it be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44040:6"/> never ſo great, it doth not defile the man; for that which is from without, <hi>doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the man, but that which is from within, Mar.</hi> 7. 15. Sin is from within; affliction is not from within, but from without, but ſin is from within: therefore if I give a reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full word to another, it more defiles me than a hundred reproachful words from another, becauſe my word comes from within me, his words from without me; Now affliction is from without, and doth not defile, but ſin is from within and doth defile; therefore the leaſt ſin is worſe than the greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take an affliction, and though it be never ſo great, yet notwithſtanding, God is the Author of it; <hi>Is there evil in the City and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> Amos 3. 6. God bad <hi>Shimei</hi> curſe <hi>David: Let him alone, God hath bidden him,</hi> 2 Sam. 16. 11. I ſend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and I ſend Peſtilence, and I ſend Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew, ſayes God; God is the Author of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, but God is not the Author of any ſin. Indeed it is ſaid God hardened the heart of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and others, but that is <hi>non infundendo malitiam ſed ſubtrahendo gratiam;</hi> not by infuſing malice into their hearts, but by withdrawing his grace; God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44040:7"/> is not the Author of ſin, but God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all affliction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take an affliction, and though it be never ſo great, yet it is not contrary to God; but ſin, though never ſo ſmall, is contrary to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Take an affliction, and though it be never ſo great, yet notwithſtanding it is but the fruit, and the Claws of ſin: What are the Claws to the Lion? if the Lion be dead, the Claws can do us no hurt, but if the Lion be alive, his life puts ſtrength into his Claws: afflictions are but the Claws of ſin, <hi>The ſting of death is ſin,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 56. and the ſting of affliction is ſin; but as for afflictions, they are but the bare Claws, and it is ſin that puts life and ſtrength into theſe Claws.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take an affliction, and though it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great, yet God doth not hate affliction, neither doth affliction make a man hate God; but God hates ſin, and ſin makes a man hate God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Take an affliction, and though it be never ſo great, a man may be a bleſſed man in the worſt affliction; <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven, and whoſe ſin is covered,</hi> Pſal. 32. 1. but he cannot be a bleſſed man that lies in sin. <hi>Curſed is every</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44040:7"/> 
               <hi>man that continueth not in all things written in the Law to do them,</hi> Gal. 3. 10. Thus you ſee, the leaſt sin is worſe than the greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, therefore certainly the evil of sin is very great. That's the <hi>9th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Look what that evil is that God doth puniſh with the greateſt ſeverity, both in His own and others, (though it be but ſmall in our eyes) that muſt needs be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding evil; Now he doth ſeverely puniſh that which we look upon as a ſmall sin, both in his own, and others. In his own, you think it was no great matter for <hi>Adam</hi> to eat the forbidden fruit; You think <hi>Moſes</hi> was but a little in paſſion with the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for which he was kept out of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan;</hi> And you think it was no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> to ſtay the Ark when it was fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: yet God puniſhed theſe ſmall sins, ſmall in our eyes, he puniſhed them ſeverely in his own people. And as for others, Becauſe there is an infinite evil in sin, and God doth juſtly puniſh, he puniſheth them to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for the leaſt sin: for amongſt men, it is juſt to puniſh till a man repenteth; but in Hell men never repent, therefore God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth them to all eternity. So that God doth puniſh sin with the greateſt ſeverity both in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44040:8"/> his own, and others; therefore ſurely it is very evil.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Look what that is, that is a worſe evil than Hell, or the Devil; that muſt needs be a very great and exceeding evil. Sin is worſe than the Devil; for the Devil is a Creature that God made, but Sin is none of Gods Creature: And it is worſe than Hell; for Hell is of Gods making too, but Sin is not; It is worſe to be given up to ſin, than to the Devil; if a man be given up to the Devil, it is that his ſoul may be ſaved; but if a man be given up to ſin, it is that his ſoul may be deſtroyed and not ſaved. So that Sin is worſe than Hell or the Devil.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Look what that evil is that is a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it ſelf, that muſt needs be exceeding evil; Sin in it ſelf is a puniſhment, though there were no other puniſhment to follow; <hi>in keeping thy Commandments there is great reward,</hi> Pſal. 19. 11. So in breaking Gods Commandments there is great puniſhment. Therefore ſometimes when God would pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh men for their ſins, he puniſheth them by giving them up to great ſins: <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 26. <hi>God gave them up to vile affections, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Now I ſay, look what that is which is in it ſelf a puniſhment, that muſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44040:8"/> needs be exceeding evil; and thus it is with ſin: this therefore muſt needs be a very great evil. Thus in the general you ſee there is a great deal of evil and sinfulneſs in sin.</p>
            <p>But now more particularly, I shall shew it you in three ſorts of ſins: The ſin of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, The ſin of our Hearts and Thoughts, And the ſin of our Lives and Practiſes; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally living under the Goſpel, the evil of theſe ſins.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, As for the ſin of our Nature, the more univerſal and overſpreading any lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie or contagion is, the worſe and the greater it is; now the ſin of our Nature ſpreads over all our faculties; our Underſtanding, Reaſon, Will, Affections; it ſpreads over all our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Look what that contagion or leproſie is, that is ſo great that nothing will help againſt it, but the pulling down the houſe: that muſt needs be very great: Truly the ſin of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſuch, nothing will cure it but the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down the houſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Look what that ſin is that is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied, and whereby a man is unwearied in ſin; that muſt needs be very great: The ſin of our nature is unwearied, as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is unwearied in ſending up water, bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44040:9"/> up water; a man may be wearied in drawing up water our of the Fountain, and ſo a man may be wearied in ſinful actions; but ſinful nature is never weary, and that ſin that is unwearied is exceeding great.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Look what that ſin is that is the ground of all our relapſes, and returns to ſin; That muſt needs be very great. Now what is the ground of all our returns to evil, after all our repentance and reformation, but our nature? Suppoſe water be heated; after it is warmed and heated, it cools again: heat it again, and it cools again: Why? Becauſe coldneſs is its nature. And ſo what's the reaſon that men return again, and again to their ſin, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their repentance and reformation, but the ſin of their nature?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Look what that evil is which is the leaſt lamented, and that whereby our ſin is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed; That is a great, and dreadful evil: Now of all ſins, the ſin of our Nature is leaſt lamented, and thereby mens ſins are moſt excuſed. Bear with me, it is my nature; I am paſſionate, but it is my nature; I am froward, but it is my nature; Men excuſe themſelves thereby. Now I ſay look what that evil is which is leaſt lamented, and that whereby our ſin is moſt excuſed; that is a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44040:9"/> dreadful evil. Thus it is with the ſin of our nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, As for the ſin of our hearts and thoughts, the evil thereof,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Look what that ſin is that is the moſt incureable; That's worſt: A ſecret hidden wound within the body, or a diſeaſe within the body, is the moſt incurable. Such are the ſins of our hearts and thoughts, ſecret ſins, and ſothe moſt incurable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Look what that ſin is that is a friend, a Parent to other ſins; That muſt needs be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evil. Now what are the Parents of all our ſinful actions but ſinful thoughts? What puts life into evil actions but ſinful thoughts? So with the godly, and ſo with the ungodly; With the Godly, for ſaith <hi>Abraham, I thought the fear of God was not in this place,</hi> Gen. 20. 11. and therefore I ſaid ſhe is my Siſter; ſhe was indeed his Siſter, and he lied not in ſaying ſo: but he diſſembled, and hid the truth, uſing an unworthy ſhift for his own preſervation; and where began this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil but in a ſinful thought? <hi>I thought, the fear of God is not in this place.</hi> So with the Ungodly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 21. <hi>Thou thoughteſt that I was alltogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf:</hi> The wicked ſteal, and commit Adultery, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44040:10"/> and ſlander others, and how are they led into all this, but by thoughts? <hi>Thou thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est I was ſuch a one as thy ſelf:</hi> and you know what the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Cleanſe thou me from ſecret faults, then ſhall I be upright, and I ſhall be innocent from the great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> Pſal. 19. 12, 13. Sins of our hearts and thoughts do principiate, and give a being unto ſinful actions, and therefore are very evil.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thereby alſo, by the ſins of our hearts and thoughts, our former ſin committed, that was dead, is revived again, and hath a reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by our muſing on it, contemplating on it with delight. As the witch at <hi>Endor</hi> called up <hi>Samuel</hi> that was dead; ſo a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thought calls up a ſinful action that was dead before. Thereby our ſins that were dead before are revived, and have a reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thereby alſo a man may poſſibly ſin that ſin in effect, which he never did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in act, and ſo the Lord may puniſh him for it: As the Lord ſaid to <hi>David,</hi> becauſe it was in thine heart to build me an houſe, I will build thy Houſe: So ſayes God to a man in a way of puniſhment, becauſe it was in thy heart to do this evil, though thou didſt it not, I will punish thee for it. Poſſibly, I ſay, by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44040:10"/> the ſin of our hearts and thoughts, a man may ſin that ſin, in effect, which he never did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in act, And that is evil.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thereby a man may or doth repent of his very repentance: A man ſins and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards is ſorrowful, and repents thereof, and then after his repentance he thinks on his ſin with delight; What is this but to to repent of his very repentance? As by my repentance I am ſorrowful for my sin, ſo by musing on my sin with delight, I repent of my repentance: Now is it not a very great evil for a man to repent of his repentance? Lo this may a man do, and this men ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily do; they repent of their repentance by musing on their sin, and delighting in it in a way of sinful thoughts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly, As for the sin of our lives and practiſe, eſpecially living under the Goſpel, the evil thereof, that is very great, for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sin under the Goſpel is ſinning againſt the remedy; and of all ſins, sinning againſt the remedy are the greateſt; and therefore it is worſe for a man to commit adultery that is married, than for an unmarried man to commit fornication; for he sins againſt the remedy. Now the great remedy againſt sin
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44040:11"/> is the Goſpel; therefore for a man to ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, he ſins againſt the remedy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The greater obligations a man ſinneth againſt, the worſe and the greater is his ſin. By the Goſpel we are brought under great obligations, and by our ſinning under the Goſpel, what do we? Weingage the very mercy of God to become our adverſary: by our ſinning under the Goſpel, we ſin againſt Mercy and Grace, and thereby ingage the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mercy of God, our greateſt friend, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our greateſt adverſary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Peccatum majus, ubi ſpecialis repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantia inter peccantem &amp; peccatum;</hi> The more repugnancy there is betwixt the ſin and the ſinner, the greater is the ſin; and therefore it is worſe for a Judg to be unjuſt, than for another, becauſe there is a ſpecial repugnancy betwixt the sin and the sinner. Now there is a ſpecial repugnancy betwixt the Goſpel, and a man that sins under the Goſpel; for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes the contrary, and therefore sin there is the greater.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Peccatum majus, ubi majus nocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> The more hurtful or miſchievous any sin is, the greater is that sin: Sinning under the Goſpel is very hurtful, to our ſelves, and to others. To our ſelve; as poyſon taken
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44040:11"/> in Sack, or ſomething that is warm, is the moſt venemous, ſo ſin under the Goſpel is the deadlieſt poyſon: Why? Becauſe it is warmed with Goſpel heat; And it is hurtful to others, becauſe they are hardened; for when men ſin under the Goſpel, others are hardened thereby.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The more able that any ſin is to defend it ſelf by knowledg, ſhifts and diſtinctions, the worſe and greater it is: Now a man that lives under the Goſpel hath knowledg, and by his knowledg is able to defend his ſin by many diſtinctions; and ſins bred under the Goſpel are able to defend themſelves by knowledg fetched from the Goſpel, therefore the worſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The more deceitful that any ſin is, and the better ends and pretences it hath, the worſe it is, and holds the longer: Now ſins bred under the Goſpel are moſt deceitful, and have the beſt ends and pretences, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The more that a man doth caſt contempt upon the great things of God by his ſin, the greater, and the worſe is his ſin: Sins under the Goſpel caſt contempt upon the great things of God, the glory of God, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious offer of the grace of God: to ſin under
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44040:12"/> the Goſpel, is to caſt contempt upon the glory of God, and the great things of God, and therefore ſin there is the greater.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The more coſtly and chargeable that any ſin is, the greater and the worſe it is: Now a man that ſins under the Goſpel can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſin at ſo cheap a rate as another, though he sins the very ſame sin that another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits: Why? <hi>He that knows his Maſters will and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes,</hi> Luke 12. 47. What an evil and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing is it for men to ſin under the Goſpel, ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>He ſhall come in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. 8. Flaming fire; not painted fire, but real fire; but there may be real fire in a ſpark, therefore he doth not ſay real fire neither; but <hi>He ſhall come in flaming fire, taking venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them that know not God, and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the Goſpel.</hi> O what an evil, and dreadful thing is it for a man to ſin living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel. Now if there be ſo much evil in the ſins of our lives and practiſes, living under the Goſpel; if there be ſo much evil in the ſin of our hearts and thoughts; if there be ſo much evil in the ſin of our nature; if ſin hath taken up all the names of all evils; if ſin
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44040:12"/> doth ſeparate between God and us; if ſin doth unite us to Satan, and make us the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil; if ſin did put Chriſt to death; if ſin doth bring a general curſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Creation; if ſin doth ſtain all our glory; if ſin doth awaken Conſcience to that horror that nothing but the blood of Chriſt can quiet it; if ſin doth feed the fire of Hell; if the leaſt ſin be worſe than the greateſt affliction; if God doth puniſh the leaſt ſin both in his own and others with the greateſt ſeverity; if ſin be worſe than Hell or the Devil; and if ſin it ſelf be a puniſhment; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly there is abundance of evil and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſin. So I have done with the firſt thing, namely, that there is a great deal of evil and ſinfulneſs in ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Though there be thus much evil and ſinfulneſs in ſin; this doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to a man until he doth convert and turn unto God: till then his ſin is dead, but then it is revived: till then the ſinfulneſs of ſin doth not appear; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Till then a man is in the dark, and who can ſee the greatneſs of an evil in the dark.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Till then grace (the contrary) is not placed in the ſoul; one contrary doth ſhew
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44040:13"/> the other: white is beſt ſeen by black; Grace is beſt ſeen by Sin, and Sin is beſt ſeen by Grace: till then a man hath no grace, no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to illuſtrate it, to make it appear.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And till then ſin is in its own place; <hi>elementum non gravidat ſuo loco,</hi> water is not heavy in its own place, it is not heavy in the River; a man may lay at the bottom of the River with all the water upon his back, and yet not feel the weight of it, becauſe it is in its place; but take but a pailful of water out of the River, and you feel the weight of it, becauſe then it is out of its place. Now till a man convert and turn unto God, ſin is in its own place, and therefore the ſinfulneſs of it doth not appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But you will ſay, How comes this to paſs that sin ſhould not appear in the sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, until a man convert, and turn unto God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Sin is a ſpiritual thing; I mean a moral, not a natural thing; Sin is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual thing, and a man that liveth by ſenſe cannot ſee what is ſpiritual.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A man is blind unto what he loves; till a man convert and turn unto God, he loves his Sin; he loves it above all the World; and therefore the evil and sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44040:13"/> of sin doth not yet appear to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The more Blinds a man hath that cover his sin, the leſs he ſees it; and the leſs sin appears to be sinful: Now before a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and turn unto God, all his duties are but Blinds to cover his sin, all his morality is but a Blind, all his natural uprightneſs is but a Blind: True (ſays he) I am a sinner; but I pray, and perform duty, therefore am not ſo great a sinner; I have ſuch and ſuch mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and my heart is as good as any ones, therefore I am not ſo great a sinner. What are all his duties before he convert and turn unto God, but ſo many Blinds to cover and hide his sin? No wonder therefore that sin doth not appear as it is, until a man doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and turn unto God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The more a man looks upon sin as going into it, the leſs it appears to be; and the more a man looks upon sin as coming out of it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it, the greater it appears to be; there is a going into sin by commiſſion, and there is a coming from it by repentance: Now when a man is going into his sin, there he ſees Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, Pleaſure, and his own concernments, and this makes his sin appear little; but when he comes out of it, there he ſees ſorrow, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and that makes his sin appear great.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44040:14"/>
            <p n="5">5. Sometimes by the providence of God, sin meets with good events; and holineſs meets with bad events in the world: and ſo the evil and sinfulneſs of sin is hidden from men.</p>
            <p n="6">6. and laſtly, The leſs a man is at the work of private examination, the leſs sin appears to be sin, and the leſs he ſees sin as it is: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man convert, and turn unto God, he is little in the work of examining his own ſoul in private: No wonder therefore sin doth not appear to him to be sinful, becauſe he is little in the work of private examination. Thus ye ſee ſin doth not appear in the sinfulneſs of of it untill a man doth convert, and turn unto God: That's the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Thirdly, Look when a man doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and turn unto the Lord, then sin appears in the sinfulneſs thereof unto his ſoul. For then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is weary and heavy laden under the burden of his sin; the more a man is weary and heavy laden under the burden of his sin, the more sin appears evil and sinfull to him: Now look when a man doth convert and turn unto God, then he is weary, and heavy laden under the burden of his sin: <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden,</hi> Matth. 11. 28.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:44040:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. Then he ſees God, and not till then; the more a man ſees God, the glory of God, the goodneſs of God, the wiſdom of God, the holineſs of God, the ſoveraignty of God; the more sin appears in its sinfulneſs to him: <hi>Wo is me, I am undone, for I have ſeen the King, the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Iſa. 6. 5. and ſayes Job, <hi>I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear, but now mine eye ſeeth thee.</hi> What then? <hi>I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes,</hi> Job 42. 5, 6. Look when I ſee God, the glory of God, the goodneſs of God, the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, the wiſdom, and the ſoveraignty of God, then sin appears in its ſinfulneſs to me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Then alſo a man comes to ſee Chriſt crucified, and not till then; there is nothing can give us ſuch a sight of the sinfulneſs of sin as Chriſt crucified: <hi>By the Law is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of ſin,</hi> Rom. 3. 20. but by the sight of Chriſt crucified, I ſee the hatred that God hath againſt sin: I do not ſee by the Law ſo much the hatred that God hath againſt sin as in Chriſt crucified; the more I ſee Gods hatred againſt sin, the more I ſee the sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it. Now look when a man doth convert and turn unto God, then he ſees Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44040:15"/>
            <p n="4">4. Look when a man hath gotten the true proſpect of Hell, and of the wrath of God, then ſin appears ſinful to him: Now look when a man convert and turn unto God in truth, then he ſees the wrath of God, and hath the true proſpect of Hell, from which he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The more a man is tired out, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the dogging and haunting of his ſin, that he can reſt no where for it, the more the ſinfulneſs of ſin appears to him: Now when a man doth convert, and turn unto God, what ſayes he? Ah; I am never at reſt, I am dogged and haunted, and tired out continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with my ſin; O now it appears very ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Look when a mans heart is filled with the love of God, and poſſeſſed with the Holy Ghoſt, then ſin appears to him to be very ſinful; for what comes the Holy Ghoſt for? <hi>To convince the world of ſin,</hi> Joh. 16. 8. Now look when a man doth convert and turn to God, then comes this convincing work of the Holy Ghoſt; then his heart is filled with the love of God, and poſſeſſed with the Holy Ghoſt; therefore then sin appears in the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs thereof unto his ſoul. And thus I have done with the Doctrine, namely, That
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44040:15"/> there is a great deal of evil and sinfulneſs in sin, which doth not appear to a man until he doth convert and turn unto God.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>By way of Application.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, For the firſt part, If there be ſo much evil and sinfulneſs in sin; behold the power of the grace of God, the grace of God with out you, the grace of God within you: If a ſpark of fire ſhould be preſerved alive in an Ocean of water, you would think it is ſome ſtrong hand that did it; If a Candle ſhould be kept light in a great wind and ſtorm, you will ſay, it was a ſtrong hand that kept it light: There is an Ocean of sin in our hearts, and that a little ſpark, or Candle of grace ſhould be preſerved in us, in the midſt of this Ocean of sin; Oh the power of the grace of God!</p>
               <p n="2">2. If this be true, Behold the riches and the freeneſs of the grace of God, that you ſhould be delivered from all this evil; sin sinful, and ſo sinful, and evil, and you deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from all this evil; oh the riches, and the freeneſs of the grace of God!</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, For the ſecond part, If the sinfulneſs of sin doth not appear until a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44040:16"/> man convert and turn unto God, Then,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here we may ſee ſome reaſon, why ſome men are not ſensible of their sins though very great, it is bccauſe they are not converted; the Commandment never came, the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not yet come: ſuch a poor ſoul goes on in his sin, and is not yet convinced of the evil of it, for the Commandment never yet came.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If this be true, what a ſad condition are all thoſe in that are not converted and brought home to God; they are in their sins, and their sin is in them; <hi>The whole world lies in wickedneſs,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 19. 1 They lie in their sin, and are full thereof; they are full of this evil; this evil is full of evil, and they are full of this evil: they are full of it. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are always filling, and never emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying: A veſſel that is always filling, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver emptying, muſt needs be full. Thus it is with a man not converted, not turned to God, he is always filling with sin, and never emptying; yea, when he thinks he is empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he thinks he is repenting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, then he is filling with sin; always filling, and never emptying, therefore muſt needs be full.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are full of it, becauſe they sin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their temptation: If a Beggar begs of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44040:16"/> me, and I give him more than he begs for; if he begs for 6 <hi>d.</hi> and I give him 12 <hi>d.</hi> he will ſay I am full, for I give him more than he begged for: ſo when temptation begs, and a man sins beyond his temptation, what doth this argue but that he is full of sin? Thus it is with men unconverted, they sin beyond their temptation, and what doth this argue, but that they are full of sin.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And full they are, becauſe they are dropping their sin whereſoever they go: You will ſay a Beggar is full of vermine, that drops his vermine whereſoever he goes; So men, not converted, not turned unto God, they are dropping their vermine whereſoever they go: if they come in good company, they are drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their vermine there; if they come in bad company they are dropping their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine there; why? becauſe they are full of vermine, full of sin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, As men not converted, not turned to God are full of sin, ſo they are under the power of it: Why? How doth that appear? Becauſe their sin commands them off from their duty. Suppoſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men sitting at table at meat together, and another comes into the room, and ſayes to one of them, Take your Cloak and follow
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44040:17"/> me, and he preſently riſes from his meat and follows him; you will ſay certainly this man is his Maſter, becauſe he ariſes from his meat at his command and follows him. So when sin ſhall command a man off from his duty, from reading the Word, from private Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; What doth this argue, but that he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of sin? As when a man is sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and grace comes and calls him off from his sin, it argues he is under the power of grace; ſo when a man is at his duty, and his sin comes and calls him off from his duty, it argues he is under the power of ſin; ſo it is with men unconverted, they are under the power of their ſin.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As a man unconverted is full of ſin, and under the power of it, ſo he knows it not; for ſin doth not appear to a man to be ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he convert and turn unto God; it doth not yet appear, as the Apoſtle ſayes in another caſe, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>It doth not yet appear what we ſhall be, but it ſhall appear:</hi> So ſay I in regard of ſin, It doth not yet appear, but it ſhall appear to a mans ſelf, and others; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man convert and turn to God, it doth not appear, but to ſuch a one it ſhall appear: when a man comes to die, and all his hoops be knocked off, then it will appear how full
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44040:17"/> of ſin he is: As a veſſel that is full of liquor, and the liquor iſſue through the hoops, you ſee there is liquor in it, but you do not know how full it is till the hoops are knocked off: But then you will ſay, O how full was this Veſſel? Ah now our hoops are on, and it doth not yet appear how full of ſin men are; onely it comes iſſuing through the hoops, through their duties, but a day is coming when all our hoops ſhall be knocked off, and then it will appear how full of ſin men are.</p>
               <p>But to the third part.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this be true, that when a man doth convert and turn unto God, then his ſin doth appear in the ſinfulneſs thereof unto him; then why ſhould we not all labour to get the true sight of sin, to be ſenſible of ſin? it is the property of a man converted to be ſenſible of sin; <hi>then ſin revived:</hi> As therefore you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to have upon you the character of a man converted, labour to be ſensible of your sin, that it may appear in the sinfulneſs thereof.</p>
               <p>It is the mind of God, that all his converted ones ſhould think much on, and be very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the sins they committed before their conversion: <hi>Such and ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are cleanſed, but ye are waſhed.</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 11. I ſay it is the mind and will of God,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44040:18"/> that thoſe that are converted ſhould be very ſensible of their sins which they committed before conversion. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thereby they pity others that are in their sins.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thereby they are kept from future sins, What is the reaſon that men are not kept from future sins, but becauſe they are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of their former sins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thereby alſo they are kept in the ſenſe of free grace towards them, and ſo they mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the free grace of God: I was a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, a Perſecutor; ſuch and ſuch a one I was; but I am waſhed, but I am cleanſed, and through grace juſtified; O the freeneſs of the grace of God! Thus they magnifie free grace. Therefore I ſay it is the mind of God, that thoſe that are converted ſhould be ſtill very ſensible of their sins committed before their Conversion: and this is a Character of a man converted, sin appears to him to be sinfull. Now therefore as you desire to have the character of a man converted, labour more and more to ſee sin in the sinfulneſs of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Well, but then the Queſtion is What shall we do, whether converted or not what ſhall we do that we may be able to ſee sin in the sinfulneſs thereof?</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44040:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Be ſure of this, that you look much upon Chriſt crucified: Chriſt on the Croſs is a glaſs wherein you may ſee the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of sin. Study Chriſt crucified much.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Labour more and more to walk in the preſence of God, the ſhines of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; For as when the Sun ſhines into the room, you ſee little motes, ſo when God ſhines into your heart, you ſee little sins: the beams of Gods countenance do diſcover sin in the sinfulneſs of it; Therefore labour to walk more in the preſence of God, and in the ſhines of his Countenance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Labour more and more to examine your own ſouls; be much in private exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: hardly an ungrowing Chriſtian that is much in private examination; hardly a proud man that is much in private examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Do you desire to ſee sin in the sinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it? Go alone, call your ſelf often to account, be much in private examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Take as much pains to keep the ſenſe of sin upon your heart as ever you did to get it: Some take pains to get themſelves into a good frame, but take no pains to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it when they have gotten it: As the Apoſtle ſpeaks, They view themſelves in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44040:19"/> glaſs of royal liberty, and go away and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what manner of men they were.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In caſe you find any particular ſin, go round about it; conſider the circumſtances thereof, aggravate it upon your own ſoul.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Improve your afflictions this way. God ſends afflictions ſometimes to give you the sight of ſome sin that lay hid before; and ſometimes your afflictions have your ſin writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on their forehead. Improve then your affliction for the diſcovery of the sinfulneſs of sin.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Be ſure you judge of sin as the Scripture judgeth of it, and not as men judge of it: the Scripture judgeth of sin by the conſequence thereof, as our Saviour Chriſt ſayes, <hi>I was an hungred, and ye fed me not; I was thirsty, and ye gave me no drink; naked, and ye clothed me not.</hi> How ſo? <hi>In as much as ye did it not to one of theſe, ye did it not to me,</hi> Mat. 25. 42, 43, 44, 45. Chriſt judgeth of sin by the conſequence of it; therefore if you would ſee sin in the sinfulneſs of it, judge of it as Chriſt judgeth of it, and as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture judgeth of it, and not as men judge of it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If you desire to ſee sin in its own colours, in the ſinfulneſs of it; then look upon the Commandments of God as great things; the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44040:19"/> more the Commandment of God is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to you, the greater will ſin be in your eye; if the Commandment of God be great in your eye, the ſin, contrary to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment will be great in your eye too.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Never think any thing ſmall betwixt God and you; there is nothing ſmall betwixt God and us, for God is an infinite God.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Never look upon ſin in the time of temptation; for then you are in the dark, and not fit to ſee the greatneſs of ſin: La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to know the difference betwixt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and corruption, and betwixt the ſins of Gods people, and others; but never look upon ſin in the time of temptation; for then you are in the dark, and cannot ſee the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of it.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And laſtly, If you would ſee ſin in the ſinfulneſs of it; then go unto God for the coming of the Commandment, that God would ſet on the Commandment upon you, as <hi>Paul</hi> here; ſays he, <hi>When the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment came ſin revived, and I died.</hi> Some, it may be here, never yet had the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſet on upon their hearts; O then go to God, and pray for the ſetting on of the Commandment upon you; then ſhall you ſee ſin in the ſinfulneſs thereof.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:44040:20"/>
               <p>Now let me add two or three cautions to this, and ſo conclude.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take heed that you do not ſo think on ſin as to forget Chriſt: If you think on ſin without Chriſt you will deſpair, if you think on Chriſt without ſin you will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume; Never think on ſin without Chriſt; Labour to get the ſight of your ſin, but never think on ſin without Chriſt; but look on your ſin in the wounds of Chriſt, and read your ſins written out in Chriſts blood.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Humble your ſelves for ſin, though it be never ſo ſmall; but do not queſtion your condition for ſin though it be never ſo great; I do not ſpeak this to thoſe that are uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, for they have cauſe to queſtion their condition for every ſin, though never ſo ſmall; but being converted and turned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, I ſay, humble thy ſelf for every ſin though never ſo ſmall; but never queſtion thy condition for any ſin, though never ſo great.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The more ſenſe you have of ſin, and the ſinfulneſs thereof, the more labour to maintain your aſſurance of the pardon of it: and the more aſſurance you have of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of your ſin, the more labour for a ſight and ſenſe of it: Let not your ſenſe of ſin quench your joy of pardon; let not your joy
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44040:20"/> of pardon hinder your ſight of ſin: if both theſe be true and genuine, the one is an help unto the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4. (And to conclude) the more ſenſe you have of ſin, the more do you come to Chriſt: for, in Scripture you ſhall find, that every good work is not for it ſelf, but ſome good works are in order to others; as for example, to inſtance in the keeping of the Sabbath, you are to reſt on the Sabbath, and it is a good work, but not for it ſelf, but in order to Prayer, Hearing, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, other duties. So here, ſenſe of ſin is a good work; but it is not for it ſelf, but in order to going to Chriſt: Therefore now go to Chriſt, and ſay, Lord, now I ſee the ſinfulneſs of ſin, let me alſo ſee the graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of grace, and the fulneſs of Chriſt; yea, now I do come to thee for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe I ſee my ſin is out of meaſure ſinful.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44040:21"/>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44040:21"/>
            <head>THE FULNESSE OF CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iſaiah, 9. 1, 2.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nevertheleſs, the dimneſs ſhall not be ſuch as was in her vexation, when at the firſt he lightly afflicted the land of</hi> Zebulun, <hi>and the land of</hi> Naphtali, <hi>and afterward did more grievouſly afflict her, by the way of the Sea beyond</hi> Jordan <hi>in</hi> Galilee <hi>of the Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The people that walked in darkneſs have ſeen a great light; they that dwell in the land of the ſhadow of death, upon them hath the light ſhined.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words do relate to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter, us you may ſee by the word nevertheleſs; in the end of the former Chapter the Prophet ſhews, that great trouble and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery ſhould befal the people of God, <hi>It</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44040:22"/> 
               <hi>ſhall come to paſs, that when they ſhall be hungry, they ſhall fret themſel<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>es, and curſe their king, and their God, and look upward,</hi> verſ. 21. <hi>and they ſhall look unto the earth, and behold trouble, and darkneſs, dimneſs of anguish; and they shall be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to darkneſs: nevertheleſs the dimneſs shall not be ſuch as was in her vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that in theſe words you have a great affliction mentioned, and the mitigation of that affliction: the affliction, or trouble, is more eaſie, and more heavy; it hath two parts, a more eaſie part, and a more heavy part; <hi>at the first he lightly afflicted the land of</hi> zebulun, <hi>and the land of</hi> Nephtali, <hi>and afterward did more grievously afflict her by the way of the Sea.</hi> The ſtory where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you have in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 15. 19. Pul <hi>the king of</hi> Aſſyria <hi>came against the land; and</hi> Menahem <hi>gave</hi> Pul <hi>a thouſand talents of ſilver, that his hand might be with him to confirm the kingdom in his hand, and</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahem <hi>exacted the money of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>ſo the king of</hi> Aſſyria <hi>turned back, and ſtayed not there in the land.</hi> There was the more light affliction: but in <hi>ver.</hi> 29. there you have the more heavy affliction; <hi>In the days of</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44040:22"/> Pekah <hi>king of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>came</hi> Tiglath-Pileſer <hi>king of</hi> Aſſyria, <hi>and took</hi> Ijon, <hi>and</hi> Abel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth-Maachah, <hi>and</hi> Janoah, <hi>and</hi> Kedeſh, <hi>and</hi> Hazor, <hi>and</hi> Gilead, <hi>and</hi> Galilee, <hi>all the land of</hi> Naphtali, <hi>and carried them captive to</hi> Aſſyria. Here was the affliction where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were vexed, both more light, and more heavy.</p>
            <p>The mitigation follows at the ſecond verſe; <hi>The people that walked in darkneſs have ſeen a great light, they that dwell in the land of the shadow of death, upon them hath the light shined.</hi> Here is an allevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this affliction by the promiſe of Chriſt, which is interpreted of Chriſt, in Matth. 4. <hi>Now</hi> (at Ver. 12.) <hi>when Jeſus had heard that John was caſt into priſon, he departed into Galilee, and leaving Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, he came and dwelt in Capernaum, which is upon the Sea-coaſt in the borders of Zebulon and Naphtali: that it might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled which was ſpoken by Eſaias the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſaying, The land of Zebulon, and the land of Nephtali, by the way of the Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles: the people which ſate in darkneſs ſaw great light; and to them which ſate in the Region, and shadow of death, light is ſprung up.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44040:23"/>
            <p>So that Chriſt, and Chriſt alone is an alleviation to our greateſt afflictions.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Doctrine that I ſhall fall in with at this time is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> There is that in Jeſus Chriſt alone-which may and can and doth afford ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent comfort and relief in the worſt of times and conditions.</p>
            <p>For the opening and proſecution whereof</p>
            <p>Firſt, We will inquire into the truth of it, that it is ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, What that is in Chriſt, that may, or can ſuccour, comfort and relieve in the worſt of times and conditions?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How far this concerns us?</p>
            <p>And ſo to the Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, As to the truth of it; it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>That in him the fulneſs of the God head dwelleth bodily,</hi> Col. 2. 9. and there is enough in God to ſupply all our wants; As there is enough in Heaven to pay for all at the laſt; ſo there is enough in God to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all at the preſent. He is too covetous whom the great God of Heaven cannot ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. When <hi>David</hi> was in the greateſt ſtrait that ever he met with in his life; his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44040:23"/> Wives, and goods taken and carried away by the enemy, and his own men and ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers mutined, and ready to ſtone him; how did he comfort himſelf, but in God? <hi>David incouraged himſelf in the Lord his God,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30. 6. There is enough in God to comfort in all conditions, and the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelleth bodily in Chriſt; Therefore there is that in Chriſt which may afford ſufficient comfort and relief in the worſt of times and conditions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you look into Scripture you ſhall find, that the promiſes and prophecies of Chriſt are calculated and given out for the worſt of times: it was uſual with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to propheſie of Chriſt; but mark how their prophecies were calculated for the worſt of times: In <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. you have a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt, Verſ. 6. <hi>In his days Judah shall be ſaved, and Iſrael shall dwell ſafely, and this is his name whereby he shall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the Lord our righteouſneſs.</hi> Well, what time doth this prophecy relate to? A very evil time: <hi>Woe be unto the Pastors that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and ſcatter the sheep of my paſture,</hi> v. 1. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>Againſt the Paſtors that feed my people, ye have ſcattered my flock, and</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:44040:24"/> 
               <hi>driven them away, and have not viſited them:</hi> and then comes in the prophecy of Chriſt. So in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. you have a great prophecy of Chriſt, ver. 16. <hi>Behold I lay in Zion for a foundation a tried ſtone, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious corner-ſtone, a ſure foundation:</hi> A plain prophecy of Chriſt: Well, but how comes this in? Why it was calculated for an evil time, at the <hi>14th</hi> Verſe; <hi>Hear the word of the Lord ye ſcornful men that rule this people which is in Jeruſalem, becauſe ye have ſaid, We have made a covenant with death, and with hell are we at agreement, when the overflowing ſcourge shall paſs through: Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold I lay in Zion for a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a ſtone, a tried ſtone, a precious corner ſtone; judgment alſo will I lay to the line, and righteouſneſs to the plummet, and the hail thall ſweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters shall overflow the hiding place, and your covenant with death shall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulled, and your agreement with Hell shall not ſtand:</hi> a prophecy concerning Chriſt, calculated for the worſt of times. So in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. you have another prophecy of Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 23. <hi>And I will ſet up one she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherd over them, and he shall feed them, even</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44040:24"/> 
               <hi>my ſervant David, he ſhall feed them, and he shall be their shepherd;</hi> plainly ſpeaking of Chriſt: VVell, but when doth he ſpeak this prophecy of Chriſt? Look into the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Son of man, propheſie againſt the shepherds of Iſrael, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and ſay unto them, Thus ſaith the Lord God unto the Shepherds; Wo be to the Shepherds of Iſrael that do feed themſelves, should not the shepherds feed the flocks? ye eat the fat, and ye clothe ye with the wool, ye kill them that are fed, but ye feed not the flock.</hi> Now in this time comes out the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Chriſt; you make mention of Aqua-vitae at other times, but when there is ſpecial mention made of Aquavitae, and the Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitae-bottle in a fainting and dying time; what doth this argue but there is a cordiality in it? the firſt time that ever Chriſt was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of, what time was it? <hi>Adam</hi> fell, and all the Children of men were in a moſt ſad condition, what cordial was then brought forth but this? <hi>The ſeed of the woman shall break the ſerpents head,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. and this is ordinary; the promiſes and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes of Chriſt are calculated for the worſt of times: why? but to teach us, that there is enough in Chriſt to comfort, ſuccour,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44040:25"/> and relieve in the worſt of times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If there was enough in the types of Chriſt, to comfort and releive the Saints and people of God under the Old Teſtament in the worſt of their times; then there muſt needs be enough in Chriſt himſelf to relieve and comfort the Saints, and people of God now in New Teſtament times, in the worſt of our times. Now ſo it was, in the times of the Old Teſtament, in caſe they had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, what relief had they? a Sacrifice to make an attonement, <hi>Levit.</hi> 4. 20. and ſo a type of Chriſt the great <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> Heb. 9. 26. in caſe they were in the wilderneſs and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bread, what relief had they? they had there, Manna, a type of Chriſt, <hi>The true bread that came down from heaven,</hi> Joh. 6. 50, 51. In caſe they wanted water what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief had they? The rock opened, and <hi>that rock was Christ,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 4. <hi>The Rock followed them, and the Rock was Chriſt.</hi> In caſe they were ſtung with the fiery Serpents, what relief had they? They had the Brazen Serpent, and that was a type of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 15. Now I ſay, if the people of God in Old Teſtament-times had relief in the types of Chriſt, ſurely there is relief enough for us now in New Teſtament times, in Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44040:25"/>
            <p n="4">4. If all the promiſes of good things made to us were origined in Chriſt, and if all the promiſes that are made unto Chriſt of good things to come do deſcend and run down upon us, more or leſs; then ſurely there is enough in Chriſt to relieve and ſuccour in the worſt of times: For what are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes but divine conveyances? Now all the promiſes of good things that are made to us, they flow from Chriſt, <hi>for all the promiſes are yea and Amen in Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 20. Yea, that is affirmed,; Amen, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; all the promiſes made to us are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and confirmed by Chriſt. And on the other ſide, all the promiſes that are made to Chriſt do deſcend upon us; Look into <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. there is a great promiſe made to Chriſt, at <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Ask of me, and I ſhall give thee the Heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion: thou ſhalt break them with a rod of iron, thou ſhalt dash them in pieces like a potters veſsel.</hi> A promiſe plainly given to Chriſt, and ſee how it deſcends and falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. Revel. 2. 26. <hi>He that overcometh and keepeth my works unto the end, to him will I give power over the Nations, and he shall rule them with a rod of iron, as the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44040:26"/> veſsels of a potter shall they be broken to shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, even as I received of my father:</hi> Even as I received of my Father, look what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe I have received of my Father, the ſame doth deſcend and fall down upon you: Now then, if all the promiſes of good things made to us were origined in Chriſt; and if all the promiſes that are made unto Chriſt of good things to come do deſcend and run down upon us, ſurely there is enough in Chriſt to ſuccour and relieve in the worſt of times.</p>
            <p n="5">5. One thing more; If that all our want of comfort and ſatisfaction doth ariſe from the want of a ſight of Chriſts fulneſs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and all our ſatisfaction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort doth ariſe from the ſight of Chriſts ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and excellency, then this Doctrine muſt needs be true: Now look into <hi>Revel.</hi> 5. and ſee how <hi>John</hi> weeps, and upon what account; <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſayes <hi>John) in the right hand of him that ſate on the Throne, a book written within, and on the backside ſealed with ſeven ſeals;</hi> and at verſ. 2. <hi>I ſaw a ſtrong Angel proclaiming with a loud voice, who is worthy to open the book and to looſe the ſeals there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and no man in heaven, nor in earth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the earth, was able to open the</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44040:26"/> 
               <hi>book.</hi> Then at <hi>ver.</hi> 4. (ſays he) <hi>I wept much, becauſe no man was found worthy to open, and to read the book, neither to look thereon.</hi> What ſtilled him, what quieted him? The ſight of Chriſt, at <hi>ver.</hi> 5. <hi>And one of the Elders ſaith unto me, weep not: behold the Lion of the Tribe of Judah, the root of David hath prevailed to open the book:</hi> ſo he goes on opening the excellency and the fulneſs of Chriſt, and <hi>John</hi> weeps no more: So that I ſay, all our want of comfort doth ariſe from our want of a ſight of the fulneſs and excellency that is in Chriſt: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certainly there is enough in Chriſt to comfort, ſuccour and relieve in the worſt of times: and ſo you have the firſt thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Well, but then ſecondly, What is that in Chriſt that may or can comfort, ſuccour and relieve in the worſt of times and conditions?</p>
            <p n="1">1. I anſwer, Firſt, Look what that good thing is which the world can either give or take away, that is in Chriſt in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; and if that be in Chriſt in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance which the world can either give or take away, then there is that in Chriſt that may or can ſuccour, comfort and relieve in the worſt of times. Now what can the world give or take away?</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44040:27"/>
            <p n="1">1. Can the world take away your Eſtate, Gold or Silver? then read what is ſaid in the third of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> concerning VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, (where Chriſt is called wiſdom) <hi>Happy is the man that findeth wiſdom,</hi> v. 13. <hi>For the merchandiſe of it is better than the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of ſilver, and the gain thereof than fine gold; she is more precious than rubies, and all the things thou canſt deſire are not to be compared unto her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Can the world take away your liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, your Goſpel liberty? Then you know what Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Behold I have ſet before thee an open door, and no man can shut it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Can the world take away your life? You know what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life,</hi> Joh. 14. 6. <hi>ye will not come unto me, that ye might have life,</hi> Joh. 5. 40. On the other ſide, what can the world give to you?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Can the world give you peace, reſt, quierneſs? Then you know what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> Matth. 11. 28. <hi>I create the fruit of the lips, peace,</hi> Iſa. 57. 19. <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you, not as the world</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:44040:27"/> 
               <hi>giveth, give I unto you,</hi> Joh. 14. 27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Can the world give you happineſs or bleſſedneſs? I am ſure Chriſt can. <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>are the poor in ſpirit; bleſsed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; bleſſed are the pure in heart: yea, bleſſed are ye when men shall revile you, and perſecute you for my ſake,</hi> Matth. 5. It was the work of the High Prieſt to bleſs the people, and Chriſt being our great High Prieſt, it is his work to bleſs us: He, and he alone can make us bleſſed. Would you therefore know what there is in Chriſt that can ſucconr, comfort and relieve in the worſt of times? Look I ſay whatſoever good thing the world can either give or take away, that is in Chriſt in great abundance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is in Jeſus Chriſt the greateſt excellency, under the beſt propriety. The greateſt excellency; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the knowledg of Chriſt be the moſt excellent knowledg, then ſurely Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf muſt needs be moſt excellent; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Jeſus Chriſt is the moſt excellent knowledg.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is the moſt certain knowledg; you know other things by their ſhapes and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, you know Chriſt by the ſpirit; you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44040:28"/> know other things by the teſtimony of men, you know Chriſt by the teſtimony of the ſpirit; and as the teſtimony of the ſpirit is more certain than the teſtimony of any man, ſo the knowledg of Chriſt is the moſt certain knowledg in the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is that knowledg that gives you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the thing you know; By my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Chriſt, I am poſſeſſed of Chriſt; ſurely therefore it is the moſt excellent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in the world, and therefore Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf muſt needs be moſt excellent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is called <hi>The deſire of all Nations,</hi> in <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 7. Some Nations deſire one thing and ſome another, but Chriſt is the deſire of all Nations: VVhat is moſt deſireable that is not in Chriſt? 1. Is Gold and Silver moſt deſireable? Sayes he, <hi>I counſel thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire,</hi> Rev. 3. 18, 2. Is wiſdom moſt deſireable? <hi>He is the wiſdom of the father,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 24. <hi>In him are hid all the treaſures of wiſdom,</hi> Col. 2. 3. He is wiſdom in the abſtract; <hi>Wiſdom hath builded her houſe,</hi> Prov. 9. 1. and it is in the plural number, wiſdoms hath build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her houſe; he is not onely wiſe, but wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and wiſdoms: And 3. He is called that good thing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33. 14. <hi>Behold the day to</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:44040:28"/> 
               <hi>come ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, that I will perform that good thing which I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto the houſe of Iſrael, and unto the houſe of Judah.</hi> That good thing, with an emphaſis, what is that? <hi>At that time will I cauſe the branch of righteouſneſs to grow up unto David, and he ſhall execute judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and righteouſneſs in the land.</hi> Chriſt is that good thing; He is <hi>the excellency of Jacob,</hi> the greateſt excellency.</p>
            <p>And this excellency is under the beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, inſomuch as you may challenge it with a double my: <hi>My God, my God,</hi> ſayes <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 22. 1. <hi>My Lord, &amp; my God,</hi> ſayes <hi>Thomas,</hi> Joh. 20. 28. There is ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in this excellency as you may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it with a double my. And it is ſuch a propriety as can never be loſt; <hi>None ſhall take them out of my fathers hand,</hi> Joh. 10. 28, 29. Would you then know what there is in Chriſt that can comfort, ſuccour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the worſt of times? I ſay there is the greateſt excellency, under the beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is in Jeſus Chriſt the greateſt fulneſs joyned with the moſt communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiveneſs: Some things are empty, and not full; ſome things are full, but they are full
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44040:29"/> of wind, as the bladders of the Creatures are, that the leaſt prick melts them down into nothing; full, but not communicative; and ſome things are communicative, but not full; as Springs, little water Springs: but Chriſt is both full and communicative; He is the <hi>Roſe of Sharon, and the lilly of the vallies, Cant.</hi> 2. 1. The roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> not the roſe of a Garden, that onely ſome can come and take the ſweetneſs of, but the Roſe of the field, that every one may come and ſmell on; his blood is a fountain opened, not a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain incloſed, but opened; He is the Tree of Life, whoſe leaves are for the healing of the Nations. So that there is not onely <hi>Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo abundantia, ſed reduntantiae;</hi> a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of abundance, but a fulneſs of redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy; flowing over in Jeſus Chriſt; Would you therefore know what there is in Chriſt that can comfort and relieve in the worſt of times? I ſay there is the greateſt fulneſs joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the moſt communicativeneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is in Jeſus Chriſt the ſweeteſt love, under the greateſt ingagement: The ſweeteſt love; <hi>Thy love is better than wine; thy name is as oyntment poured forth, therefore do the virgins love thee,</hi> Cant. 1. 3. <hi>Greater love than this hath no man,</hi> ſaith Chriſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44040:29"/> concerning his death, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 13. There is love in Chriſt beyond all dimenſions; there is height and bredth, and length, and depth, of love in him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 18, 19. 1. There is giving love in Chriſt, <hi>who loved us, and gave himſelf for us,</hi> Gal. 2. 20. Epheſ. 5. 25. 2. There is forgiving and pardoning love in Chriſt; witneſs <hi>Peter,</hi> whom Chriſt forgave when he had denied him. 3. There is in Chriſt condeſcending love, witneſs <hi>Thomas; Come Thomas</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>reach hither thine hand, and thrust it into my ſide,</hi> Joh. 20. 27. I condeſcend to thee. 4. There is in Chriſt accepting love. <hi>I tell thee</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>whereſoever this Goſpel is preached, that which this woman hath done, ſhall be told for a memorial of her,</hi> Matth. 26. 13. accepting of what ſhe did. And 5. There is in Chriſt a ſympathizing love; <hi>For he is not ſuch an High Prieſt as cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities,</hi> Heb. 4. 15. There is the ſweeteſt love in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And it is under the greateſt ingagement; for, is not a brother ingaged to help his brother? <hi>He is not aſhamed to call them brethren,</hi> Heb. 2. 11. Is not a Father en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to help his Children? <hi>He is the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father,</hi> Iſa. 9. 6. Is not a Husband engaged
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44040:30"/> to help his Wife? The Church of Chriſt is his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> Cant. 4. 9. And now ſuppoſe there were one perſon that could ſtand under all theſe relations; a Brother, a Father, a Husband; how much would that perſon be engaged to help, that ſhould ſtand under all theſe relations? Thus Chriſt doth, he ſtands under all theſe relations; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there is in Chriſt the ſweeteſt love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the greateſt ingagement.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There is that in Jeſus Chriſt that ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to all conditions; what condition can you come into but there is a promiſe ſuited to it? and what are the promiſes but the veins wherein the blood of Chriſt doth run? There is no condition but hath a promiſe ſuited to it, and ſo there is that in Chriſt that ſuits to all conditions. To inſtance a little:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are you poor and needy? <hi>I counſel thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire, that thou mayeſt be rich,</hi> Rev. 3. 18. 2. Are you naked? (ſayes he) <hi>I counſel thee to buy of me white raiment, that thou mayeſt be clothed, and that the ſhame of thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs do not appear.</hi> 3. Are you out of the way, wandering? <hi>I am the way,</hi> Joh. 14. 6. 4. Are you in the dark in reference to any buſineſs or your condition? <hi>I am the</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44040:30"/> 
               <hi>light,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>and the light of life, Joh.</hi> 8. 12. 5. Are you hungry? <hi>I am the bread of life,</hi> Joh. 6. 48. 6. Are you thirſty? <hi>I am the water of life? He that drinketh of the water that I ſhall give him ſhall never thirſt more,</hi> Joh. 4. 14. 7. Do you need Juſtification? <hi>He is the Lord our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 23. 6. 8. Do you need Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication? <hi>For this cauſe do I ſanctifie my ſelf that they alſo may be ſanctified,</hi> Joh. 17. 19. 9. Do you need Conſolation? <hi>I will ſend the comforter,</hi> Joh. 16. 7. 10. Do you need Protection? <hi>He is the rock of ages; the Lord Jehovah,</hi> Iſa. 26. 4. 11. Are you in a Paradiſe of Proſperity? He is the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> Rev. 22. 14. 12. Are you in a wilderneſs of adverſity? He is <hi>the Manna</hi> that came <hi>down from Heaven,</hi> Joh. 6. 50. So that then, there is that in him that is ſuited to all conditions.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is that in Jeſus Chriſt that doth anſwer to all our fears, doubts and objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Hearken if there be ever a poor doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul here; There is that in Chriſt that doth anſwer to all thy fears, doubts and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</p>
            <p>VVill you ſay, I am a poor loſt Creature? Then ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I came to ſeek and to ſave</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:44040:31"/> 
               <hi>that which was lost,</hi> Luke 19. 10. Will you ſay, oh but I am a ſinner, a great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? Saith Chriſt, <hi>I came not to call the righteous but ſinners to repentance,</hi> Mat. 9. 13. Will you ſay, oh but I cannot repent? Then ſee what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 31. concerning Chriſt, <hi>Him hath God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted with his right hand to be a Prince, and a Saviour, to give repentance unto Iſrael, and remiſſion of ſin:</hi> not onely remiſſion of ſin, but repentance: It is Chriſts work to give repentance as well as forgiveneſs of ſin. Will you ſay, oh but I cannot leave my ſins, I cannot turn away from my ſins? Then read what the Apoſtle ſaith, Act. 3. 26. <hi>Unto you firſt God having raiſed up his Son Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning away every one of you from his iniquities.</hi> Will you ſay, Oh but I cannot come to Chriſt? Then he tells you that he is come to you; <hi>I came to ſeek, and to ſave that which was loſt:</hi> He brings the loſt ſheep home upon his ſhoulder, as in the Parable. VVill you ſay, Oh but his ſheep follow him, and I cannot follow him? Then he tells you, <hi>He will carry the Lambs in his armes, and gently lead thoſe that are with young,</hi> Iſa. 40. 11. He will drive you at your own pace. Will
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44040:31"/> you ſay, Oh but I have provoked Chriſt, and he is angry and will caſt me off? You know what he ſayes then; <hi>Thoſe that come unto me I will in no wiſe caſt out,</hi> Joh. 6. 37. He is meek and lowly; He is meek, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will not be angry with you; he is lowly, and therefore will not diſdain you: <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>for I am meek and lowly, Matth.</hi> 11. 29. VVill you ſay, Oh but I have ſinned to the very utmoſt, Then the Apoſtle tells you, that <hi>He is able to ſave to the uttermoſt,</hi> Heb. 7. 25. So that there is plainly that in Chriſt that anſwereth to all our fears, doubts and objections.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Yet one thing more. There is that in Jeſus Chriſt which doth and will ſupply all our wants: VVhat is there that you want? Do you labour under deſertion? Then ſaith he, <hi>I will lead you in a way that you have not known,</hi> Iſa. 42. 16. <hi>And I will never leave you nor forſake you.</hi> Heb. 13. 5. Do you labour under corruption and bondage to ſin? There is freedom in Chriſt; <hi>Thoſe the Son makes free are free indeed,</hi> Joh 8. 36. indeed really, indeed eminently; <hi>Thoſe the Son makes free are free indeed;</hi> indeed and indeed. Do you labour under great Temptations? It is he that <hi>treads down Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44040:32"/> 
               <hi>under our feet,</hi> Rom. 16. 20. and, ſaye he, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 9. Do you labour under the want of the means of grace, or the miniſtery of the VVord? <hi>He hath received gifts for men;</hi> and what thoſe gifts are, the Apoſtle tells you, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11. Apoſtles, Prophets, Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, Paſtors and Teachers. Do you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under weakneſs, ſpiritual infirmity? Then he hath ſeven Horns, and ſeven Eyes, as you find him deſcribed, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5. 6. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to your infirmity or weakneſs; or do you labour under any affliction, outward or inward, under perſecution from ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? Then ſee what is ſaid concerning Chriſt, Micah 5. 5. <hi>And this man ſhall be the peace when the Aſſyrian ſhall come into our land.</hi> Are you afraid of an enemy coming into the land? <hi>This man ſhall be the peace when the Aſſyrian ſhall come into our land.</hi> This man, VVhat man? See at verſ. 2. it is plainly ſpoken of Chriſt. <hi>But thou Bethlehem Ephratah, though thou be little among the thouſands of Judah, yet out of thee ſhall come forth unto me, that is to be ruler in Iſrael, whoſe goings forth have been from of old, from everlaſting, &amp; he ſhal ſtand and feed in the ſtrength of the Lord, in the</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:44040:32"/> 
               <hi>Majeſty of the name of the Lord his God, and this man ſhall be the peace:</hi> This man, that is Chriſt; he ſhall be our peace when the worſt of enemies come into our land.</p>
            <p>Aye, but you will ſay, we ſee no likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of this; mark then what is ſaid at <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>And the remnant of Jacob shall be in the midſt of many people as a dew from the Lord, and as the showers upon the graſs that tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth not for man, nor waiteth for the Sons of men.</hi> If a Garden be to be watered with a watering pot, it ſtayes for man; but if it be watered with the dew, it ſtayes not for man: So ſaith the Lord, Shall the remnant of my people be, as the ground that waits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the dew, that tarrieth not for man; Though you ſee no likelihood of deliverance, no means whereby ye ſhould be delivered, when the Aſſyrian comes into our land, when the worſt of enemies come into our land; yet ye ſhall be delivered, For <hi>this man shall be the peace:</hi> So that look whatſoever that is which you want, it is all to be had in Chriſt. And thus now you ſee in theſe ſeven Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, what there is in Jeſus Chriſt that may and can and doth afford ſufficient comfort and relief, in the worſt of times and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, That's the ſecond.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44040:33"/>
            <p n="3">III. Well but then you will ſay in the third place, This is good in the general, but what is this to us? We know there is enough in Chriſt to ſuccour, comfort and relieve in the worſt of times and conditions, but what is this to us?</p>
            <p>Yes, it is to you, and to you very much; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you be overcommers and do over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the evil of the times and places where you live, then all this fulneſs and excellency that is in Chriſt doth belong to you; for if you look into the ſecond and third Chapters of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> you ſhall find, that unto every Church there mentioned, there is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made of giving out ſome of the fulneſs and excellency of Chriſt; and ſtill the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe runs to him that overcometh, at the end of every Epiſtle: <hi>To him that overcometh;</hi> that is, to him that overcometh the evil men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that Epiſtle; not in the general, but the evil mentioned in that Epiſtle. As now to inſtance in the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> ſaith he, chap. 3. 21. <hi>To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh, will I grant to ſit with me in my Throne; even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father in his Throne</hi> What is the thing promiſed here? Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt in his Kingdom on Earth.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44040:33"/> Well, but who are thoſe that ſhall partake thereof? Such as overcome; <hi>to him that overcometh.</hi> That overcometh, what? That <hi>Laodicean</hi> Lukewarmnes; The ſin forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in this Epiſtle is luke-warmneſs, a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the worſhip of God: He that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh this mixture, he ſhall have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt in his Kingdom on Earth. Now I ſay, this fulneſs and excellency of Chriſt is promiſed to him that overcometh. Then (friends) you know what the evils of the times are; if you overcome the evils of the times wherein you live and are, then ſhall you be made partakers of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and fulneſs of Chriſt, and ſo this concerns you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt hath therefore received all this excellency and fulneſs from the Father, that he may give it out to you; then it concerns you, and much concerns you. Now why hath Chriſt received all this excellency from the Father? why hath he received the ſpirit? why was he annointed with the ſpirit? He tells you in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord God is upon me, becauſe the Lord hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed me.</hi> Why? <hi>To preach good tidings unto the meek, he hath ſent me to bind up</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44040:34"/> 
               <hi>the broken hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound:</hi> for this cauſe was I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. And why hath our Lord and Saviour Chriſt received gifts? The Apoſtle tells us, and the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>for men, for the rebellious alſo, Eph.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Pſal</hi> 68. 18. Will you ſay, oh but I am a poor Rebel? he hath received gifts for men, for wicked men, even for rebels; <hi>Paul</hi> was a Rebel, and Chriſt received gifts for <hi>Paul,</hi> even that rebel. And why hath he received all power in Heaven and Earth from God the Father, but in reference to your concernments <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 18. <hi>Jeſus came and ſpake unto them ſaying, All power is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> What then? <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, and loe I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world.</hi> Go ye therefore; mark what a there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is here: <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven, and in Earth; Go ye therefore;</hi> Jeſus Chriſt hath received all power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth in reference to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments; therefore it is much to you, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44040:34"/> there is that in Jeſus Chriſt whereby he is able to ſuccour, comfort and relieve in the worſt of times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet thirdly, If that our Lord &amp; Saviour Chriſt doth therefore ſtoop to your infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, becauſe he is clothed with Majeſty and Excellency, and inveſted with all this power; then this that I have ſaid is to you, and much to you: Now look into <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. you have there an aſſurance of what you ſhall find in Chriſt now, by what he did then when he was to die, at verſ. 3. <hi>Jeſus knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands, he riſeth from ſupper, and laid aſide his garments, and took a towel and girded himſelf: after that he poureth water into a baſon, and began to waſh the Diſciples feet.</hi> Whence doth this ariſe? See at verſ. 3. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands;</hi> He was not therefore proud, he did not therefore diſdain his poor Diſciples; No: but he did condeſcend to them upon this account, and ſtoops to their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: his humility prompts on his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be good to us. Now if he therefore ſtoops to your infirmity, becauſe he is clothed with excellency, then this that I have ſaid is to you, and much to you.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44040:35"/> And ſo you have the Doctrine cleared.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now by way of Application.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If this Doctrine be true, that there is that in Jeſus Chriſt alone, which may and can and doth afford ſufficient comfort and relief in the worſt of times and conditions; what a mighty encouragement is here for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to get into Chriſt, to get an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt? Get but an intereſt in Chriſt, and you have a ſtanding relief in the worſt of times and conditions: No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, no relief in the worſt of times. Who would not get an intereſt in Chriſt? If there be any ſuch here that are yet without an intereſt in Chriſt, man or woman, conſider what there is in Chriſt; there is (as you have heard) that in Chriſt that will afford ſufficient comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in the worſt of times: Times are evil, O be encouraged to get an intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If this Doctrine be true, Why ſhould we then complain? why ſhould we be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in ſuch times as theſe, or any time or condition we can come into? <hi>Shall the living man complain,</hi> Lam. 3. 39. Shall a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44040:35"/> living Chriſtian complain, that hath a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving relief by him? The book of Job ſayes of the wicked, <hi>That in the fulneſs of his ſufficiency he shall be in ſtraits,</hi> Job 20. 22. and shall we be in ſtraits in the midſt of Chriſts ſufficiency? Shall we complain, or be diſcouraged, when we have Chriſts ſufficiency for our relief at all times? You have heard of that woman, who when ſhe met with any loſs, would ſtill comfort her ſelf thus; True, I have loſt ſuch a Child, or I have loſt ſuch a friend; ſuch a friend, or ſuch a relation is dead, but ſtill God is alive: and when ſhe had loſt her Husband, and cried and lamented very much, her Child came to her and asked her; But Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is your God dead? So may men ſay to us, while we complain and are diſcouraged in theſe times, Is your God dead? Is your Saviour dead? But either there is a reality in this Doctrine or not; if not, why doth the Scripture ſpeak at this rate as you have heard? and if there be a truth in this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, why ſhould we be diſcouraged, or complain whatever our condition be?</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this Doctrine be true, why ſhould we not own Chriſt in the worſt of times? why ſhould we not confeſs Chriſt in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44040:36"/> worſt of times? Shall Chriſt be our relief in the worſt of times, and ſhall we not own and confeſs him in the worſt of times? Shall we not own his truth, and wayes, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and confeſs them before the Sons of men in the worſt of times? When the Sun ſhines ſcorching hot, men run to the ſhadow of the tree; and when it rains much, men run under the tree for ſhelter; but when the heat is over, and the rain over, the tree ſtands alone, and no man looks af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. So long as the Sun ſhines upon the Dial, you will run to the Dial; but when the Sun is off the Dial, you come not at it. So when the times ſhine upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the truths and ways of God, many will run to them, but when the ſhine is gone, and truth be in the dark, the Sun off: How few will own Chriſt and his truth? But if this Doctrine be true, why ſhould we not own and confeſs Chriſt in the worſt of times?</p>
               <p n="4">4. If this Doctrine be true, here you may ſee, what an evil thing it is to ſin againſt Chriſt. It is to ſin againſt our remedy, our relief; it is to ſin againſt our ſuccour; of all ſins thoſe ſins are worſt that are againſt the remedy: Therefore (as I uſe to ſay) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44040:36"/> in married perſons, is worſe than Fornication in thoſe that are unmarried, becauſe it is againſt the remedy. Chriſt is our remedy, our relief, in the worſt of times; therefore to ſin againſt Chriſt, Oh what a great ſin is it? It is to ſin againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
               <p>Now 1. Look when men offend the weak brethren in things indifferent, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayes expreſly, they ſin againſt Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And look when men and women will not believe, notwithſtanding all the offers of grace and love that Chriſt makes to their ſouls; then they ſin againſt Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And look when a Profeſſor, a member of a Church ſhall walk ſcandalouſly, haunt Taverns or Alehouſes, or deal unjuſtly, and is a diſhonour to the name of Chriſt, he ſins againſt Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And look when men perſecute the wayes and people of Chriſt, they ſin againſt Chriſt. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecutest thou me? Act.</hi> 9. 4. Theſe, and many other wayes do men ſin againſt Chriſt; and O what an evil thing it is to ſin againſt Chriſt, it is to ſin againſt the remedy, the greateſt remedy in the world: Take heed how ye ſin againſt Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:44040:37"/>
               <p n="5">5. If this Doctrine be true, that there is that in Jeſus Chriſt, which may and can and doth afford ſufficient comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in the worſt of times and conditions; then here we may ſee, what we ſhould do, and whither we ſhould go for relief; why ſhould we not go to Chriſt for relief in all conditions, and relieve our ſelves in him upon all occaſions? If there were a ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign water that would cure all diſeaſes, what flocking of people would there be unto that water: Here is that water, that ſoveraign water; Chriſt alone, that can cure all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, that can ſuccour and relieve in the worſt of times: Why ſhould we not now come to him, and draw water out of this well of ſalvation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> But you will ſay, I confeſs indeed Chriſt is the well of ſalvation, and there is enough in him to ſuccour and relieve; but the well is deep, and my line is ſhort, and my arm is weak, and I know not how to get this water: I know not how to improve Chriſt; What ſhall I do that I may be able to draw water out of this well of ſalvation? what ſhall I do that I may improve Chriſt, for my ſuccour and relief in the worſt of times and conditions?</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:44040:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If you would draw water out of this well of ſalvation, and improve Chriſt for your relief and ſuccour; be ſure of this, that you look upon Chriſt as the great inſtitution and appointment of the Father for all thoſe ſuccours and reliefs that are in your eye. In the ſixth of <hi>John,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ye ſeek me, not becauſe ye ſaw the miracles, but becauſe ye did eat of the loaves, and were filled:</hi> But at verſ. 20. ſayes he, <hi>Labour not for the meat which periſheth, but for the meat which endureth unto everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life.</hi> Where ſhall I have it? <hi>Which the Son of man ſhall give unto you.</hi> How ſhall I get it from him? Look upon him as the appointment of the Father, <hi>for him hath God the Father ſealed,</hi> him hath God the Father appointed; look upon him therefore, and go to him, as the great appointment of the Father for the very thing you want.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be ſure of this, that you make good your intereſt in Chriſt; get aſſurance of your intereſt in him; elſe you will be afraid to come at him; For <hi>all things are yours</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>whether Paul, or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death:</hi> Why? <hi>For ye are Chriſts,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 21, 22, 23. But if you be not aſſured of this, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44040:38"/> ye are Chriſts and Chriſt yours; how can ye relieve your ſelves in Chriſt in an evil day? Get therefore an aſſurance of your intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Obſerve what thoſe attributes and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of Chriſt are which are moſt ſuited un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your condition, and lay them much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and preſs your hearts therewithal; it is not enough for us to come to Chriſt in the general, but we muſt come to him, and deal with him according to thoſe attributes, or titles, that are ſuited to our condition: Chriſt is willing we ſhould do ſo, and hath on purpoſe clothed himſelf with ſuch titles as ſuit our condition; the ſecond and third Chapters of the <hi>Revelations</hi> are a proof of this very thing; all the Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches begin with titles of Chriſt; in the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> there is one title; in the Epiſtle to the Chuch of <hi>Smyrna</hi> there's another title, and ſo to all the ſeven Churches: Every Epiſtle begins with a ſeveral title of Chriſt, and according to the condition of the Church he writes to, ſo is the title he begins with. As to inſtance in the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> at the <hi>8th.</hi> verſe, there his title is, <hi>The firſt and the laſt, which was dead, and is alive,</hi> Rev. 2. 8 Why this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44040:38"/> title? He writes to the Church in Smyrna that was to ſuffer hard things, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer, behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon:</hi> Is that all? Is the Priſon all? No, ſayes he, <hi>Be thou faithful unto death, ye shall have tribulation ten dayes:</hi> relating to the ten perſecutions in the Primitive times, dying times: VVhat then? Now remember my titles, my attributes; this is my name and title; the firſt and the laſt, which was dead, and is alive: ſee how this title ſuited to their condition. And (friends) aſſure your ſelves of this, that Chriſt will certainly make good his titles that he is clothed with: <hi>David</hi> aſſured himſelf of it, <hi>The Lord is my she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherd.</hi> VVhat then? <hi>I shall not want,</hi> Pſal. 23. 1. He will make good his title, I know I ſhall not want; he relieved himſelf in that title of Chriſt that ſuited his condition. So do you do this day: As for example. Is there diſtreſs among the Saints and people of God? remember his title, he is the <hi>King of Saints,</hi> Rev. 15. 3. Is there great diſtreſs of Nations? remember his title, he is <hi>King of Nations,</hi> Jer. 10. 7. Are you under any dimneſs or vexation? (as it is in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) remember his title, <hi>A light is riſen up,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44040:39"/> 
                  <hi>a marvellous light.</hi> Thus be ſure you deal with Chriſt according to that title of his that is moſt ſuited to your condition.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Be ſure of this, that you ſtudy Chriſt and your condition together; ſome ſtudy their condition, ſtand poreing upon their condition, but they do not ſtudy Chriſts; and they are full of unbelief: Some think much on Chriſt, but not on their own condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and they are given to Preſumption: But would you find true relief in Chriſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your condition be? Then ſtudy Chriſt and your condition together; as thus; Chriſt is a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet: if you be ignorant, now think on Chriſt as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; if you be guilty, now think on Chriſt as a Prieſt; if you be diſorderly, now think on Chriſt as a King. Thus ſtudy Chriſt and your condition together.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Be ſure of this, that you put Chriſt upon it, to ſuccour and relieve you in the worſt of times; to do that for you that he hath entitled himſelf unto: So <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. See how he argues, and his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is exceeding good; <hi>Lord,</hi> (ſayes he <hi>ver.</hi> 2) <hi>Be thou my ſtrong rock:</hi> why? <hi>for thou art my rock,</hi> verſ. 3. Lord, this is thy name, this is thy title: <hi>Thou art my rock;</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44040:39"/> then <hi>be my rock:</hi> and ſayes he, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Pull me out of the net that they have laid privily for</hi> me, <hi>for thou art my ſtrength.</hi> I have to deal with enemies, and they have laid their net privily for me; <hi>Pull me out of the net that they have laid privily for me, for thou art my ſtrength.</hi> So now, popiſh men have laid their net privily for us, and we may go to Chriſt and ſay, Lord pull us out of the net that they have laid privily for us, for thou art our ſtrength. Thus put Chriſt upon it to anſwer his titles.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If you would find ſuccour, comfort and relief in Chriſt in the worſt of times and conditions; then reſt upon him in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all other helps and ſhifts, or unlawful means of deliverance, in caſe you come into any ſtrait: Chriſt is ſo much yours, as you reſt upon him; as our reſting on the promiſe makes it ours, ſo our reſting on Chriſt makes him ours. And you know how graciouſly the Lord appear'd to the three Children; Chriſt came and walked with them in the fiery furnace, and delivered them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 25. How ſo? They reſted or him: <hi>We know that our God is able to deliver us, we will not bow down to the Idol,</hi> whatever comes on us: <hi>We know our God is able to deliver</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:44040:40"/> 
                  <hi>us,</hi> ver. 17, 18. here they reſted upon him alone in oppoſition to all unworthy ſhifts, and unlawful means for deliverance, and then Chriſt appeared and gave out his ſuccour and relief to them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If you would find ſuccour, comfort and relief in Chriſt upon all occaſions, and in all conditions, then go to God by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; go and beg of God to open your eyes, that you may ſee this fountain that is by you; it is poſſible that your eyes may be held, as <hi>Hagars</hi> were; <hi>Hagar</hi> had the Fountain by her, but ſhe did not ſee it, for her eyes were held: And thus it is with many of us; Chriſt our Fountain is by, and we even ſit down in deſpair: why? for our eyes are held. Go then to God and beg of him to open your eyes that you may ſee this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And laſtly; If you deſire to draw wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of this well of ſalvation, and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove Chriſt for your relief and comfort in the worſt of times; then obſerve what thoſe promiſes are, that the Lord hath made to his people for the latter times, and be ſure that you deal much with them: Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and relieves by promiſes: As the Devil tempts by promiſes, ſo Chriſt comforts by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44040:40"/> promiſes; and when a man is relieved by a promiſe that Chriſt hath made, he is relieved by Chriſt. Now there are nine or ten pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that the Lord Chriſt hath made to the latter times for the comfort of his people, to be as a relief for his people in theſe latter times, I will but barely name them, and ſo conclude.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He hath promiſed them, that they ſhall have underſtanding in the times, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>The wicked ſhall do wickedly, and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. He hath promiſed, that they ſhall be ſealed, ſet apart, hidden in the worſt of times, in Antichriſtian times, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the <hi>9th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. He hath promiſed, that though they meet with Antichriſtian tribulation, they ſhall come out with their garments waſhed in the blood of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Theſe are they which came out of great tribulation, and have waſhed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the lamb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord hath promiſed to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in theſe latter times, that they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in his temple day and night; that is, they ſhall enjoy the Ordinances of God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44040:41"/> without interruption; though now they are ſcattered and driven from the Houſe of God, the Lord hath promiſed ſuch a time wherein they ſhall be in the Temple day and night without interruption, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 15.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He hath promiſed to deſtroy all their Antichriſtian enemies: <hi>Babylon is fallen,</hi> it is fallen, <hi>and as a milſtone is thrown into the Sea; ſo ſhall Babylon be thrown down, and ſhall be found no more at all,</hi> Rev. 18. 21.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Lord hath promiſed, that his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall propheſie, though they be in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, they ſhall bear witneſs to the truths and wayes of God, and ſhall propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 3. <hi>I will give power unto my two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and they ſhall propheſie</hi> 1260 dayes. I will give them power, they ſhall propheſie and not be ſilent.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He hath promiſed alſo, that the light and glory of his people ſhall be more than ever it was, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 26. <hi>Moreover, the light of the Moon shall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun shall be ſeven fold, as the light of ſeven dayes.</hi> When is this? <hi>In the day that the Lord bindeth up the breach of his people, and healeth the ſtroak of their wound.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:44040:41"/>
               <p n="8">8. He hath promiſed to his people, that they ſhall ceaſe from their labour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 13. <hi>Bleſsed are the dead which die in the Lord,</hi> (that die for the Lord) <hi>henceforth they rest from their labours, and their works do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them.</hi> There ſhall be a time here on Earth wherein the Saints ſhall reſt from their labours.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Lord hath promiſed, that the number of his people ſhall be much increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. When the enemy went about to cut off all the males of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then the Iſraelites were much increaſed: And this the Lord hath promiſed, that in the latter dayes, his people ſhall be greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: When the witneſſes ſhall riſe (I do not mean an inſurrection, but a reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) it is ſaid, <hi>they aſcend in a cloud,</hi> a company of people as a cloud ſhall come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, to gratifie them in their riſing; <hi>And there shall be a great earthquake, and in the earthquake ſlain of men</hi> 7000, <hi>and the remnant shall be affrighted, and give glory to God,</hi> Rev. 11, 12. 13. There ſhall be a great increaſe.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And laſtly, The Lord hath promiſed, that the Saints ſhall rule the world, and the government ſhall be given unto them; not,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44040:42"/> that any should go about to wreſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment out of the hands of the preſent powers; but in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 27. the Lord hath promiſed, <hi>That the kingdom and dominion, and the greatneſs of the kingdom under the whole heaven shall be given to the people of the Saints of the moſt high, whoſe kingdom is an everlaſting kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe ten things the Lord hath promiſed to his people in the latter dayes: thoſe that lived in the Apoſtles dayes, they comforted themſelves in theſe promiſes then; they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted themſelves in the book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> then; the book of the <hi>Revelations</hi> is a book on purpoſe for the comfort and relief of the people of God in Antichriſtian times: and if it was a comfort and relief to them in the Apoſtles dayes, what may it be unto us upon whom the laſt dayes are come? Chriſt comforts by promiſes, and when a man is comforted and relieved, by a promiſe made by Chriſt, he is comforted by Chriſt, and Chriſt hath given out theſe great promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the latter times. Now you ſee into what times we are fallen: Are the times e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil? do they grow worſe, and will they yet grow worſe, before they grow better? then remember this Doctrine, and comfort your
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44040:42"/> ſelves therein; There is that in Jeſus Chriſt alone, that may and can and doth afford ſufficient comfort and relief in the worſt of times and conditions. Go then to Chriſt upon all occaſions; do not let relief ſtand by, and not uſe it; Chriſt takes it kindly that you make uſe of him, and the more you uſe him, the more kindly he takes it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
